and today we are going to learn how to
use the powerful notion formula language
to extend our notion databases with
custom functionality if you don't know
what it is notion is a powerful project
management tool that integrates with
your document note and wikis notion is a
connected workspace where you create
docs take notes manage tasks and
organize your life's work all in one
place by combining many different tools
teams can efficiently manage projects
with much more speed and Clarity and by
using the formulas we are about to see
you can make your notion databases much
more useful and Powerful many people
don't know this but notion has a formula
system with functions operators
constants and properties that uses the
syntax of the JavaScript programming
language we can write formulas in our
databases to run all kinds of
calculations and functions based on
other property so let's say that we are
hosting an event and have a database of
guests these database has two columns
name and last name if we wanted to have
a column that displays the full name all
we have to do is create a new column
with the type formula then after we
click on the edit button we will see a
prompt where we can write our code to
get the value of one column into our
formula we use the prop function with
the name of the column we want to select
in our case we want to get the value of
both name and last name and put them
together to put values together we can
use the built-in concat function this
function concatenates or puts together
all its arguments and returns their
result so putting it all together we are
going to write concat and inside of it
we are going to use the prop functions
to select the name and last name columns
as you can see the formula works but we
have to add an extra space in between
and we're done the formula is now
created for all the rows in our column
so when we add the next frame to our
database the value will be calculated
automatically apart from being able to
manipulate strings of text notion
formula functions can do pretty cool
stuff with dates back in our guests
database we now have a birthday column
that has a type of date using formulas I
would like to calculate how old my
friends are after creating a new column
with the formula type and clicking on
the edit button we can use the date
between function the date between
function takes three arguments two dates
and a unit for the first date we are
going to use the Now function that gives
us the current date for the second date
using the prop function we will select
the birthday column on the unit argument
we can write years quarters months weeks
days hours minutes seconds or
milliseconds depending on what unit we
want to get the difference on in our
case we will write years and we are good
to go and just like that we can get the
age of our friends in an automatic way
because some of our guests are under 18
I would like like to have a column that
tells me if the guest can drink a beer
or not after creating a new column with
the formula type and clicking on the
edit button we will use the larger or
equal function this function receives
two arguments and it will return true if
the first argument is larger than or
equal than the second so we write larger
EQ and get the value of the previously
calculated H column using the prop
function then we write 18 as the second
value now our database tells us who is
and who isn't allowed to drink beer at
our event as you can see our formulas
can use values from other columns that
are formulas themselves when we
calculate if the guest can drink or not
we are using the value of the H column
which as you remember is a value that
another formula calculated before so
what do you think Super useful right
let's jump into another database this
time where we are managing a project
this database has three columns the name
of the project the project you date and
the checkbox that tells us if the
project is completed or not we are now
going to make a new formula column to
calculate if the project is overdue or
not after creating a new column with the
formula type and clicking on the edit
button we are going to use the IF
function the IF function takes a
condition and two values if the
condition is true the first value will
be returned and if it isn't the second
one will be for the first value we are
going to check if the current date using
the Now function is greater than the
value of the new date column if it is we
are going to return the text overdue and
if it isn't we are going to return the
text on track it works well but as you
can see the last project on the list
comes out as overview even though it is
finished to fix this we are going to
write a nested if first we will check if
the checkbox of the finished column is
check if it's equals to true we will
return a text that says finish if the
column is not checked then the second if
will run and here is where we check if
the value of now is greater than and
review date and return the appropriate
text to practice everything that we have
learned so far on another column let's
calculate for how long the project has
been overdue or how many days until the
due date here is the formula it's kind
of big so let's go through it part by
part first we are checking if the
project is completed if it is we return
a check Emoji if it isn't we are going
to return a string that says for example
two days overdue or two days until
deadline we first use the date between
function to calculate the difference in
days between now and the due date of the
project that will give us a number that
might be positive or negative depending
on the project being overdue or not
because we don't want to display
negative numbers we use the app's
function this function is used to get
absolute numbers which means that if we
give this function -1 it will return one
then we use the format function which
takes the number and turns it into a
text that we can use on the concat
function that we saw before and finally
we check if today's date is bigger than
the due date of the project we know the
project is overdue and so we attach a
days overdue text as we write this on
the deadline and that's it our project
database is looking great as you can see
the only way we can know if the project
is completed is by checking the
completed checkbox to finish up let's
improve that part instead of having to
check a box manually let's make it
automatic if all the tasks of a project
are completed then the completed box
should automatically be calculated as
true for this we are going to create
another database with the tasks for all
our projects and these database will
divide the tasks by their status not
started in progress and done on our
project database we are going towards a
new relationship column to the tasks
database then we are going to connect
each task to their projects we can then
hide the relationship column and we can
proceed to create a roll up column A
roll-up column allows us to count
specific objects on another database in
our case we want to get a percentage of
the tasks that have the status of
completed we then choose if we want to
see this count as a number a progress
bar or a ring we can now go back to our
completed column and turn it into a
formula type we will use the prop
function to get the value of the roll up
column which is a value between 0 and 1
1 being a hundred percent and we will
just check if the value is equals to one
if it is the column will be checked and
else it won and we are done now when I
complete tasks on my tasks database we
will see the progress of the project
being updated on the Project's database
and when all tasks for a specific
project are completed the completed
column will be set to True which will
also trigger some changes on the status
and the overdue list formula we did
before as you can see using the power of
formulas you can super charge your
notion databases to make them even more
useful managing is hard and even though
formulas are very magical there is a
limit to what they can do this is why
notion is sponsoring this video because
they want me to tell you about their new
product notion projects notion project
is notion specifically optimized for
project management instead of using a
ton of tools to manage your projects we
can use notion projects to do all in one
place notion projects centralizes all
your workloads into one place meeting
notes lunch plans issue tracking Sprints
brainstorms and more it also has a super
useful AI integration that we
demonstrated on a video a while ago that
can summarize meeting notes right ideas
to-do lists and more it also has a slack
figma and GitHub integration for issues
and pull requests it's basically notion
on steroids for project managers get
started with notion projects for free by
clicking the link below
see you on the next one bye
thank you